September 18, 1931. Japan, in search of raw materials for
feed its growing industry, invades Manchuria, an industrial area located in
Northeast China known for its rich mineral and coal reserves.
In the following years there will be several "incidents", or armed confrontations of
limited character, between the Empire of the Rising Sun and the Republic of China,
but a full-scale war between the two countries will not break out until the Incident of
Marco Polo Bridge, July 7, 1937. This marks the beginning of World War II.
Sino-Japanese War that only ended with Japan's surrender on September 2, 1945.
During this conflict, a prelude to World War II in the Pacific,
The Japanese army achieved important victories, capturing Beijing and Shanghai. In December 1937,
The Japanese army invades Nanjing, then the capital of China. In this
city, Japanese soldiers commit unspeakable atrocities and undertake
a campaign of mass murder that, over the course of two months,
will claim the lives of up to 300,000 civilians and numerous unarmed Chinese soldiers. One
Among those responsible for these cruel acts is Japanese Major General Moritake Tanabe.
Moritake Tanabe was born on February 26, 1889 in Ishikawa Prefecture, Japan. Like
that his father, a former samurai and later colonel in the early Imperial Japanese Army,
Moritake also wanted to be a soldier. After attending military preparatory schools,
Tanabe graduated from the Imperial Japanese Army Academy in
1910 and at the Army Staff College in 1918.
Early in his career, Tanabe served on the staff of the 16th Division,
based in Kyoto, which was one of the four new infantry divisions created by the
Imperial Japanese Army in the aftermath of the Russo-Japanese War of 1904–1905.
Tanabe then served as an instructor at the Army Academy,
Military attaché in France, commander of the 61st Battalion of
Infantry and Army Maintenance Office staff member.
After serving as an instructor at the Army Infantry School
From Toyama between 1933 and 1934, Tanabe was head of the Economic Mobilization Section of the
Ministry of the Army. He returned to the battlefield to command the 34th Regiment.
Infantry from 1936 to 1937, before his promotion to major general in August
1937 and returned to the Toyama Army Infantry School as its commandant.
Returning to the armed conflict in Asia between Japan and China
It began with the invasion of Manchuria, long before the official start of World War II.
As part of previous treaty agreements, the Japanese had troops protecting the
railway in southern Manchuria. However, Japan wanted to expand its control over Manchuria
China, so on September 18, 1931, the Japanese placed a small explosive device
along the tracks of the Japanese South Manchuria Railway, near the city
of Mukden. The ensuing explosion became known as the Mukden Incident. Although the damage to the
railway were minimal, served as an excuse for the Japanese to quickly and unauthorizedly take over
said city, present-day Shenyang, and to seize all the towns located along the
railway. Despite Chinese opposition, the Japanese continued to advance and on February 27
From 1932 the last Chinese who opposed the takeover were forced to surrender. Now,
All of Manchuria was in Japanese hands. On March 1, they established the puppet state
of Manchukuo, which was not dissolved until August 18, 1945, after the Emperor
Japanese Hirohito announced the unconditional surrender of his army 3 days earlier.
The Japanese army invaded Manchuria without the approval of the civilian government of their country and without
declare war, violating the rules of the League of Nations. There were two reasons
main reasons for the invasion. The first was that Japan had a highly developed industry,
But the land lacked natural resources. As a result, he turned to Chinese Manchuria.
in search of oil, coal, rubber, timber and other raw materials to compensate for the lack
of resources in Japan. The second reason was that Japan viewed Manchuria as a buffer state.
against the invasion of its interests by the Soviet Union from Siberia.
As the invasion attracted great international attention, the League of Nations
sent a task force called the Lytton Commission to investigate the attack. The commission,
which delivered its findings in October 1932 and was chaired by Lord Lytton,
He blamed the Japanese for the attack, claiming that the Land of the Rising Sun was the
aggressor, had unjustly invaded Manchuria and that it should be returned to the Chinese. He also
maintained that the Japanese puppet state of Manchukuo should not be recognized. On 27
In March 1933, Japan formally notified its withdrawal from the League of Nations.
Since the invasion of Manchuria, there have been several "incidents", or armed clashes of
limited character between the Empire of Japan and the Republic of China,
but all had ended up remitting. However, this changed the night of
July 7, 1937, when a small Japanese force maneuvered near the Marco Bridge
Polo demanded to enter the small walled city of Wanping to look for one of its soldiers.
However, the city's Chinese garrison denied entry to the Japanese;
A shot was heard and both sides began fighting. The Chinese government,
Under strong anti-Japanese pressure, he refused to make concessions in negotiating the dispute.
and the Japanese also maintained their stance. As a result, the conflict continued to escalate.
The importance of the Marco Polo Bridge Incident lies in the fact that, after it,
Tensions did not subside again, but rather escalated, with greater forces
committed by both sides. Thus, the fighting quickly spread to other parts of China. After
The Marco Polo Bridge Incident, which marked the beginning of the Second Sino-Japanese War
or War of Resistance Against Japanese Aggression between 1937 and 1945, the Japanese
They won important victories, capturing Beijing, Shanghai and the Chinese capital of Nanjing
in 1937. This led to the Nanjing Massacre, also known as the Rape of Nanjing.
With the outbreak of the Second Sino-Japanese War, Tanabe was appointed Chief
of the General Staff of the 10th Imperial Japanese Army in October 1937. It was
of a new organization dependent on the Japanese Central China Area Army,
created as an emergency reinforcement force to complement the Expeditionary Army
Japanese in Shanghai after the Battle of Shanghai, which lasted from August 13 to February 26.
November 1937, and was one of the largest and bloodiest battles of the entire war,
later described as "Stalingrad on the Yangtze". It is also often referred to as
the battle that started World War II. After more than three months
After intense fighting on land, sea and air, the confrontation ended with a victory for Japan.
The battle can be divided into three stages, and almost a million people participated in it.
of soldiers. The first stage lasted from August 13 to 22, 1937, during which the Army
The National Revolutionary Army of the Republic of China attempted to eradicate the presence of Japanese troops.
in central Shanghai. The second lasted from August 23 to October 26, 1937, during the
which the Japanese launched amphibious landings on the coast of Jiangsu and the two armies
They fought a house-to-house battle similar to that of Stalingrad, in which the Japanese tried
to take control of the city and the surrounding regions. The final stage, on October 27
At the end of November 1937, it consisted of the withdrawal of the Chinese army in the face of maneuvers by
Japanese flanking, and the ensuing battle on the road to China's capital, Nanjing.
General Iwane Matsui, who expelled the army
Chinese from Shanghai and had under his command the 10th Army of Tanabe,
He had made it clear to his superiors that he was determined to capture China's capital, Nanjing,
Located 300 kilometers west of Shanghai, Matsui stated forcefully and confidently that
The war with China would not end until Nanjing was under its control,
and predicted that the fall of the city would lead to the total collapse of Chiang Kai-shek's government.
Moritake Tanabe participated with his 10th Army in the Battle of
Nanjing and the subsequent atrocities known as the Nanjing Massacre.
Although the massacre is generally described as having occurred over a period of
Six weeks after the fall of Nanjing, the crimes committed by the Japanese army
were not limited to that time period. Many atrocities were reportedly committed.
as the Japanese army advanced from Shanghai to Nanjing. Perhaps the most cruel
Notorious was the organization of a killing contest between two Japanese officers,
as reported in the Tokyo newspaper. The contest - a competition between the two
officers to see who could kill 100 people first using only a sword - was covered
like a sporting event with regular updates on the outcome over several days.
The Japanese army continued to advance, breaking the last lines of resistance
China and arriving at the gates of Nanjing on December 9.
With reports of Japanese brutality, most of the civilian population had already fled
from Nanjing out of fear. Wealthy families were the first to flee their homes,
Leaving Nanjing in cars, followed by the evacuation of the class
middle and then the poor, while only the destitute lower class,
like the Tanka boatmen, were left behind. Three-quarters of
The population had fled Nanjing before the arrival of the Japanese.
Foreigners in Nanjing created the Safety Zone in the city, managed by a Committee
International specific to this area, directed by the German businessman and member of the party
Nazi John Rabe. The area and the activities of the International Committee were responsible for
protect 250,000 Chinese civilians from death and violence during the Nanjing Massacre.
It was a safe haven in the city for women, children, and other non-combatants. The troops
The Japanese respected the Zone to a certain extent. Until the Japanese occupation, no missiles
entered that part of the city, except for a few stray shots. However, during the chaos that
followed the attack on the city, some died in the Security Zone, but the crimes that were
produced in the rest of the city were much greater according to all indications.
At noon on December 9, the Japanese military dropped leaflets over the city,
urging the population of Nanjing to surrender within 24 hours. They promised to show "no mercy" if they
rejected the offer. No response was received from the Chinese before the date
December 10 deadline and General Iwane Matsui waited another hour before
give the order to take Nanjing by force.
artillery and aerial bombardment, General Tang Sheng-chi, commander of the Nanjing garrison
during the siege of the city, who had previously announced that he would not surrender and would fight until the
death, ordered his men to retreat. What followed was chaos; some Chinese soldiers
They stripped the civilians of their clothes in a desperate attempt to go unnoticed,
and many others were shot by the Chinese surveillance unit as they attempted to flee.
On December 13, the 6th and 116th divisions of the Japanese army
They were the first to enter the city, facing little military resistance.
Beginning on December 13, 1937, Japanese soldiers committed random killings,
rape, looting, arson and other war crimes. They persecuted and
They killed suspected Chinese soldiers and summarily arrested thousands of local youths. Many
Innocent men were wrongly identified and killed in the process.
Thousands were taken to the Yangtze River, where they were machine-gunned until
death. Many Chinese soldiers were blown up with landmines,
Then they doused them with gasoline and set them on fire; those who survived were killed.
with bayonets. Japanese soldiers also beheaded several Chinese prisoners of war.
The invaders also massacred families living outside the Security Zone and
They raped tens of thousands of women. In one case, a Chinese woman, Mrs. Ha,
asked the Japanese soldiers why they had killed her husband. Before finally
kill her and her baby by plunging a bayonet into her chest, raping her and shooting her.
The number of Chinese women raped by Japanese soldiers ranged from 20,000 to 80,000,
including some children and the elderly. A large number of sexual abuses were carried out
systematically by soldiers when they went door to door, looking for girls. Thus,
Many women were captured and gang-raped. Although immediately afterward, these were
often killed by cruel mutilations. A former Japanese soldier named Shiro Azuma spoke
frankly about the rape and murder trial in Nanjing: "Nothing would happen if only
We raped them. I shouldn't say it's okay. But we always stabbed and killed them. Because
corpses do not speak." Some evidence of these cases is due to the fact that after
being raped by Japanese soldiers, the victims were often photographed.
There are also accounts of troops coercing families to commit incest.
sons to rape their mothers, fathers to rape their daughters and brothers to abuse
her sisters. Instead of punishing the Japanese troops responsible for the rapes
Major, "the Japanese expeditionary force in Central China issued the order to establish
comfort houses during this period. The "comfort women" or "girls"
"comfort women" were forced into sexual slavery by the Imperial Japanese Army
in countries and territories occupied before and during World War II.
The Japanese army also looted the city and burned many buildings,
One third of the city was destroyed as a result of arson.
These crimes lasted from three to six weeks.
Up to 300,000 civilians and numerous unarmed Chinese soldiers were killed in the
the course of two months. Chaos, fires and mass graves make
an accurate count of casualties is impossible. The violence subsided in February 1938,
after the establishment of a Chinese-led, Japanese-influenced government. The unit
Tanabe's group that participated in the atrocities was officially dissolved in Nanjing on 14
February 1938 and in October of the following year he was promoted to lieutenant general. From March to
In November 1941 he was Chief of Staff of the Japanese Army in the North China Zone.
At the end of 1941 Tanabe was called back to Japan to serve as
position of Deputy Chief of Staff of the Imperial Japanese Army. He held
this position at the time of the attack on Pearl Harbor. He strongly opposed
both the attack on the naval base and the declaration of war on the United States.
Before the offensive, many Americans were reluctant to get involved in the war in Europe.
This changed when his country declared war on Japan, an ally of Nazi Germany, which
entered fully into World War II. Tanabe favored a defensive strategy
consisting of attracting the Allies to campaigns in areas far from their bases
hoping to stretch their supply lines to Japan's benefit. This
He was instrumental in ending the disastrous attrition of Japanese forces on Guadalcanal.
In April 1943, as conditions began to deteriorate for Japan throughout
From his southern front in the Pacific War, Tanabe was sent to Sumatra occupied by
Japan in the Dutch East Indies. His mission was to assume command of the 25th Army,
under the responsibility of the Japanese Seventh Area Army at Fort de Kock. In Sumatra,
The Japanese had systematically mistreated prisoners of war by forcing them to build
a railway that could transport coal and move troops across Sumatra. In its
As mentioned above, Tanabe was not interested in the health and well-being of these workers.
Moritake Tanabe remained at his post in Sumatra for the remainder of the war.
Official statistics from the People's Republic of China on its civilian and military casualties in the
The Second Sino-Japanese War from 1937 to 1945 resulted in 20 million deaths and 15 million wounded.
At the end of the war, Moritake Tanabe was arrested by the Dutch authorities and
sent to Medan, in the Indonesian province of North Sumatra,
where he faced a Dutch military tribunal.
Tanabe was tried there for crimes in the Dutch East Indies. Crimes,
That is, not related to those committed during the Nanjing Massacre, of which he,
As Chief of Staff of the Japanese 10th Army, he was responsible.
On December 30, 1948, the Dutch military court sentenced him to death by hanging.
Tanabe was 60 years old when he was executed on July 10, 1949.
No tears were shed for Moritake Tanabe.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to like and subscribe
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss it
our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel